A Guide to the William Newton Hale Papers, 1940-1950
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
William Newton Hale Papers 1940-1950
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11646-b
This collection contains ca. 450 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The materials were donated by Mrs. Lucy McIlwain Hale on April 26, 2001.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains an additional group of the drawings and business papers of Charlottesville architect William Newton Hale, Jr. (1920-1954). Included are ca. 450 items, contained in 1 Hollinger box, 1 oversize box, and 10 oversize folders, covering mainly the years 1951 through 1954.
Contents List
- Client Files
  - Art Prints & Post Card n.d. (Box 1)
  - "Hale" (Prof. Practice Materials and Legal) 1947-1953 (Box 1)
  - Holmes, Amy Hale 1944, 1948, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - Horse Show Program 1940 (Box 1)
  - Hudson, E. F.; Red Hills Proffit, VA 1951 (Box 1)
  - Hudson, E. F.; Red Hills (Farm Buildings) 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - Miss Ruby Smith Residence-North Garden, VA 1952 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings October 1951 (Box 1)
  - Notes to Clients, etc. & Practice Thoughts 1952 (Box 1)
  - Office Announcement, Tickets and Photograph (Commonwealth Court) n.d. (Box 1)
  - Student Work (Sketches and Tests) n.d. (Box 1)
  - Sketch, Garden Shed (Meadowbrook Road?) n.d. (Box 1)
  - Sketch Pad n.d. (Box 1)
  - Sam Estes, Stanardsville n.d. (Box 1)
  - Unlabelled File [Sketches (Juvenile Work)] n.d. (Box 1)
  - W. N. Hale Army Work 1943 (Box 1)
  - Folder 1: Magazine Clipping - Idea Files n.d. (Oversize 68)
  - "Italy- 1420 AD - Breviary Leaf" 1420 (Oversize 68)
  - Better Homes and Gardens April 1949 (Oversize 68)
  - Holiday October 1953 (Oversize 68)
  - Telephone Directory, Charlottesville November 1951 (Oversize 68)
  - SMALL BOX OF ARTIFACTS, containing the following: (Oversize 68)
    - Framed picture, UVA West Range n.d. (Oversize 68)
    - Penhurst Place Bookmark n.d. (Oversize 68)
    - Small black drafting straight-edge n.d. (Oversize 68)
    - Pencil Pointer Flint Paper n.d. (Oversize 68)
    - Carter's Household Indelible Ink n.d. (Oversize 68)
    - Erasers (2) n.d. (Oversize 68)
    - Tube, Flake White Paint n.d. (Oversize 68)
    - Small paint caps (3) n.d. (Oversize 68)
  - Study for Entrance "Perrywood" n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 1)
  - Study for wellhead "Perrywood" n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 1)
  - Perspective sketch of 2-story house (w/genie on carpet) n.d., 1 photocopy on foam core (Oversize 1)
  - perspective sketches of Hale Residence #2, 1923 Meadowbrook Road n.d., 2 sheets pinned to foam core backing (Oversize 1)
  - Charcoal portrait sketches; student work c.1940, 7 sheets (Oversize 2)
  - Watercolor studies, still life c. 1940, 7 sheets (Oversize 2)
  - Presentation boards; student projects; interiors c. 1940, 3 sheets (Oversize 2)
  - Watercolor study of woman w/ blond hair & gown c. 1940, 1 sheet (Oversize 2)
  - Sketch for Howard Johnson's Placemat n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 3)
  - Plan for Unknown House w/ gambrel roof n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 3)
  - Prelim. Study- Guest House at "Perrywood" sketch n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 3)
  - Prelim. Study- Guest House at "Perrywood; plan n.d., 1 sheet (Folder 3)
  - Yellow Frame house; perspective sketch n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 3)
  - Front porch area, Alger House n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 3)
  - Arthur Whitehill Residence; plan n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 3)
  - Chippendale-style Highboy furniture; sketch n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 3)
  - Unknown church addition ("Sunday School Area") n.d., 2 sheets (Oversize 3)
  - David Smith Residence, Greenwood, Virginia n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 3)
  - 5 sketch plans taped to 1 large white sheet n.d. (Oversize 3)
  - Hale Res. #2, Meadowbrook Rd. "Porch Detail" c. 1947, 1 sheet (Oversize 5)
  - Addition for Unknown House; plan n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 5)
  - Unknown 2-story House, front elevation n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 5)
  - Orbin Carter Residence interior details 1953, 1 sheet (Oversize 5)
  - Alterations to Holsinger Building 1951 (Oversize 5)
  - Unknown House; "View from the Southeast" n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 5)
  - Addition to A.G. Bigelow House, 1717 Rugby Rd. n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 5)
  - "Perrywood"; "Wellhead Details" 1947, 1 sheet (Oversize 5)
  - "Perrywood"; "Entrance Detail" 1947, 1 sheet (Oversize 5)
  - Marvin-Savage House; sketches n.d., 19 sheets (Oversize 5)
  - Hudson Job, Profitt, VA n.d., 12 sheets (Oversize 6)
  - Worthington Cabin, Alterations n.d., 6 sheets (Oversize 6)
  - Worthington House, Stoney Point n.d., 10 sheets (Oversize 6)
  - Ruby Smith House; Alterations n.d., 10 sheets (Oversize 6)
  - Hale Residence #1 (2022 Hessian Road) 1946, 28 sheets (Oversize 7)
  - McLennan Residence Alterations (2022 Hessian Road) 1954, 3 sheets, stapled (Oversize 7)
  - Southern College, Petersburg VA n.d., 10 sheets (Oversize 8)
  - Spicer Mill Farm Subdivision, Orange VA 1954, 17 sheets (Oversize 8)
  - Amy Hale Holmes Residence; sketches (2029 Hessian Road) c. 1950, 3 sheets (Oversize 9)
  - Amy Hale Holmes Residence; plans 1950, 2 sheets (Oversize 9)
  - Hale Residence #3 (10 Deer Path, Belair) 1953, 8 sheets (Oversize 9)
  - Hale Residence #2 (1923 Meadowbrook Rd.) 1947, 18 sheets (Oversize 9)
  - Robert Neal Residence Addition (1923 Meadowbrook Rd.) working drawings 1954, 6 sheets stapled (Oversize 9)
  - Study for Hale House #2, Meadowbrook Rd 1947, 1 sheet (Oversize 10)
  - Hudson, E. F., Red Hills, Proffitt, Va. Farm Buildings c. 1952, 4 sheets (Oversize 10)
  - Hudson, E. F., USDA Plans- Farm Buildings c. 1952, 8 sheets (Oversize 10)
  - H. J. Redfield, Study for Residence; 1733 Dairy Road 1950, 2 sheets (Oversize 10)
  - Interior Details-Unknown Houses n.d., 3 sheets (Oversize 10)
  - Studies for Unknown House (4 elevations) n.d., 1 sheet (Oversize 10)
  - Studies for traditional houses in Early American, Irish, Norwegian, Dutch styles (probably student work) c. 1940, 1 sheet (Oversize 10)
  - Axonometric section of house (probably student work) c. 1940, 1 sheet (Oversize 10)
  - Charcoal Sketches, still life and house (student work) c. 1940, 2 sheets (Oversize 10)
  - Charcoal sketches; portraits of two unidentified women; (student work) c. 1940, 2 sheets (Oversize 10)
  - Mrs. S. D. Blackford-Alterations to Cottage n.d. (Oversize 10)
  - Framing Diagram, "Spottswood Road House" n.d. (Oversize 10)
- Student Design Exercises c. 1939-1943 (Oversize 4)
  - Arch Design B
    - Church and Parish Hall
    - Art Museum
    - "An Inn with Cottages"
  - Arch Design B-I
    - "Small Suburban Library"
    - Red Brick Industrial Building